and it's really good for young dharma
students you know to do some kind of
heavy work around the
house so you can volunteer for diamond
mountain
they have lots of hard jobs here
and it's a big part of dharma practice
okay and you don't get spoiled you don't
get soft you know you become a
hard
core dharma person if you clean a lot of
toilets and
you know
my special job was to clean up after
ceremonies
and it's amazing how dirty buddhists can
be at a ceremony
and
they used to eat all of the llama tupa
and then they would leave and there'd be
200 dirty dishes and there'd be cakes
all over the floor and
many years 25 years and
so i think it's a
valuable part of dharma
training but you know
i was the only westerner in his home so
uh
i can't do that with you guys
there's no time okay anyway
it's good to learn to clean toilets
okay
i think at three jewels they do pretty
good i mean people help right pretty
well yeah it's a culture
there is
there is a direct correlation okay
now let's look at uh meditation number
17.
i have to keep doing some okay and i'll
do more book after the retreat
uh
meditation number 17 is uh
the mind goes automatically to it and
part of taking refuge
is to
keep
pictures and statues
and books around your house okay i like
gail says house because it's a very
buddhist house
they're everywhere under everything
there's some buddhist thing
there's pictures everywhere there's a
song cover on the heater little so if
you look close you can see some copper
he's in the heater
you know and uh
i was like hi i can see you
you know and
you know
so
uh there's a part
in the long room
that's you know
we're kneeled some copyings
we don't
i mean we rather go to a dci event then
go to a temple and wave incense right
but
it's a very good custom
to keep
lots of buddhas in your house okay so mr
wu
there's no room to sit in his house
because it's all buddhas
you know and
that's a good habit okay jewish people
have a custom
to put a special
thing at the door right what's it called
i don't know
huh
[Music]
anyway they have this thing
and uh
i decided i want a buddhist one so i got
a little buddha from uh
sarnot where buddha first thought you
gave it to me or no
candygate no
xiaoping
you gave me in varanasi a little buddha
who gave it to me
from where buddha first taught
then i carved a hole in my near my door
and i glued it
in there you know so every time i come
and go i have to see this buddha's
looking at me you know
in the lam rim it says that's a very
good custom
okay
why
when you have trouble you will think
about buddhists okay so
generally
it's important jewish people have
another good custom
you're not allowed to make a statue of
god
right
like
in their temple there's no images
because they say it's impossible
to make a picture of a holy being not
possible
so you're not allowed to try
but and i used to think you know i don't
need all these buddhas around you know i
just have to clean them right
so i'm like
i don't need them
i used to have them they got dusty my
llama said clean them i said i don't
want to
then
you know i decided i just won't have any
you know but uh
what the lamrim says about refuge
it's part of refuge to keep buddhas in
your house okay it could be tara
it could be chiang kang yuja mole
it could be anything okay but just keep
them
where you have to see them i put one on
the refrigerator because that's my real
altar
you know i'm always going there
for refuge
and uh
you know so i put one of those a
magnetic one on on the refrigerator
it's always looking at me
okay so
it's a custom
so
the idea is and if you have books all
over your house buddhist books
you know it's a tradition to keep some
above your head
where you walk into your house
on the inside up above the door
and there's a custom to keep them above
your head where you sleep okay
and it's a custom not to keep them where
your feet are pointing on your bed okay
so not at the end of your bed
notebooks or buddha
pictures
where the feet of your when you sleep
your feet are facing them put them on
the other side near your head
and uh maybe some place where you can
see them when you fall asleep right so
i have some images
you know in my bedroom and they're
i have tony llamas collected works above
my head i figured that's the best thing
and then i have all the buddhas around
that and so kapa's right there okay so
it's part of going for refuge
to keep images around you all the time
because when you die it will stay in
your mind okay
it will stay in your mind when you get
in a car accident when you get cancer
when you're lying on the bed in the
hospital the last time
your mind will go to that you see your
mind will go to what you saw your whole
life okay
so keep lots of things around
it's not uh
buddhist home decorating okay and it's
not a competition
my buddha is more valuable than your
buddha you know
mine is silver mine is gold yours is
just
wood you know it's not like that okay
but keep them around we have a nice
image of my teacher there
uh anton from moscow mc helped us to
make it
and uh
so it's nice to have your teacher's face
around there's its own carpet over here
and uh
there's a tonkata here
and
some of my teachers are here so uh keep
keep images around keep books around
little stupas okay
uh the pictures represent buddha
the books represent dharma
sorry the stupas are buddha
mind
body mind and speech in in tibet
language
we don't say altar we say uh
the place where buddhist body speech and
mind live okay so
body is
uh image
speeches you keep a book there like
ching chang jing
and in mind is you keep a smile stupid
there
and then that's a good altar it has
three things body speech and mind okay
uh so
during this meditation
you can just think about
part of retreat
is to make plans
for after you get home
okay part of the experience of retreat
is to make plans for when you get out of
retreat okay so
i i when i do retreats i keep a journal
i always bring an empty journal
and maybe in the evening i sit down with
my hot chocolate and i write
if i have good ideas you know like oh
i need a buddha over my
my front door or something like that
then i make a note because i will forget
when i get on the airplane
you know i'll forget everything so
keep a journal
you shouldn't talk during these retreats
any retreat you shouldn't talk uh
even if you're staying with other people
try not to talk someone talks to you
just go like this
okay don't talk back all right and
it's a it helps to retreat
i didn't i don't know many many many one
month retreats
during my business career
and
uh the first time i felt a little bit
nervous i thought oh
uh
i will
my business will get worse you know if i
go away for one month
then my business will get worse you know
i was worried about it
and i waited for a long time then i
finally i did my first retreat
in a bedroom next to my llamas bedroom
and i stayed in the bedroom for one
month and
some other monk brought me food and
stuff like that then
when i came out i had all these ideas
about acip to create acip
to save all the books and now it's 31
years right
so
you don't waste your time in between
okay
it feels like you are going to get
behind
in your work
all the other people will get the good
position
and your work will be worse or something
like that but
what i learned was all my cool ideas
came during lay room during retreat one
month retreat
so
i encourage you to do it
and and bring a journal with you when
you do this retreat okay
don't forget
okay
uh
let's look at the schedule uh okay
we talked about monday already
then uh tuesday seven in the morning
do the first part of this book okay and
i told you
you don't have to finish it it's pretty
long okay
do it for half an hour
mark where you stop
and you're welcome to stop if you find
something cool
like oh i want to do a lot of extra
offerings or i had a bad week and i want
to do a lot of confessions then you can
stop and do a lot of confessions okay
you
fit the book to you and not you to the
book
okay if you need more
confession time take more confession
time if you need more rejoicing time
take rejoicing time okay
then 7 30 on tuesday
you're gonna do
the first uh let me see how many parts
there are
you're gonna do the first
five meditations okay in here first five
okay
you can pick
it's only 45 minutes the first session
so
you can pick
something from the first five
okay
then uh you do your own yoga
and then you eat
and then important is 10 15 to 11.
when you do retreat
you have to take rest time okay don't be
like scott or read
work all day all night okay
you have to take a break
it makes you smarter
okay so take a nice break
no responsibilities no guilt
just goof off
don't do anything don't think about
dharma
okay
think about everything else okay but
take a
just take a nice break okay don't feel
guilty all these dharma people feel
guilty if they take a break okay
it's a big part of dharma that you learn
to relax okay and take some time off
okay
then when you come back your practice
will be much better
okay but if you never take a break your
practice will get worse and worse okay
uh
11 o'clock
the second part of this book okay called
thousand angels okay
so copper prayer
do that
and then uh
you do the second five meditations
something from meditation six to number
ten okay you choose
then you take a break you can do a
little bit of stretching you can walk a
little bit okay walk around
12 30 to 1 30 is
is one long hour
just mantra okay
you can do that some kappa mantra in
your own language okay if you prefer
okay
yeah uh you can do it out loud you can
do it
silently but but they say
a loud whisper is ideal
okay
loud whisper
then the spirits can hear you okay
uh it's on kappa manta right
um
what's it gonna say
[Music]
it's not a waste of time
okay i used to think mantras were a
waste of time
i didn't want to do mantras i just
wanted to study books
my teacher forced me to do retreat my
teacher took all my books away
say just do mantras i say it's boring i
don't want to just do mantras
but it's powerful and it works and now i
believe it okay uh just do mantras don't
look at anything
and see where your mind goes okay and
it works okay it's a very good practice
[Music]
it's a very good practice okay it seems
like superstition or something it's not
it's very very good for you okay so just
do mantras
your mind don't try to control your mind
uh
during the mantras
uh what i'd like you to think about
is people who helped you in your life
okay just
long
list
of people who helped you in your life
you know
the first day you will say geshe-la
i can't do that for an hour because
there's only five people
okay
then start a list okay keep a paper
every time you think of someone who
helped you a lot write it down
then by the end of the three days you
will have two or three hundred people
there who helped you a lot but you never
think about them okay so keep a list
it's very good practice keep a list you
know
my mother carried me for nine months and
almost died to give me my life okay
number
one and then
you will find tier 300 and it's a
beautiful practice and it makes you
a very nice person it makes you a good
person okay so just think about
people who helped you since you were a
kid okay or since when you were
adopted inside your mom
okay
then 1 30 to 2 30 you can take a walk
outside
uh there's a rule
about walking in retreat
what's the first rule
no don't go outside of the boundary okay
so there's a retreat boundary
don't go outside of the retreat boundary
uh
yeah second rule where i had
okay i had the pleasure
in the last few years because i used to
surf
i was in the sun all day
i got this got cut off here okay big cut
and here i got a big cut it's a skin
cancer okay from sun
okay so you don't want it it's not fun
they cut deep they have to cut it out
okay so don't so wear a hat okay don't
be a tough guy
and cover your arms
okay cover your hands
i'm getting there okay number one number
two wear some sunscreen
you know put it on
don't be stupid okay wear it okay
don't be a tough guy okay everybody i
know who doesn't wear it got skin cancer
okay so don't do that
uh
and drink lots of water okay
drink a lot of water take water with you
okay if you get lost you're gonna need
water okay
you can't survive in this desert for
more than a day or a day and a half
without water it's not possible okay you
need water
don't get lost okay
don't go where you cannot see a building
okay
don't go someplace where you cannot see
a building i got lost here
and i i helped to build all these
buildings okay
so it's possible so be careful stay stay
on the road
okay and
keep a building inside okay all right
agree
okay
uh
then 2 30 have a light snack don't eat
too much okay uh
i got some nice instruction from anatol
some of you know anatol he he gave me
some
eating instructions
recently and
it was very helpful for me
and maybe we can talk about it
it's a buddhist diet you know you can
eat something
vegetarian and healthy and it's very
light
i lost a lot of weight like i don't know
six kilos seven kilos and uh
it's very good for your health
so uh maybe i'll teach you after the
retreat okay it's very helpful
and it's healthy and it's vegetarian
okay
all right
so don't eat too much because you can't
meditate if you eat too much okay
uh 3 to 3 45
the next
part of the meditations which is 11 to
okay
meditations 11 to 15 okay
[Music]
pick one or two
focus on those
then 3 45 to 4 15
there's a joke some yoga teacher had a
joke
when you feel tired from sitting in
meditation too long you have two choices
you can do some yoga stretches or you
can eat
chocolate and the yoga stretches don't
make you fat
okay
yoga stretches are good for you okay
then 4 15 to 5 15
you can do walking meditation
do much oh by the way if you're walking
and you meet somebody
the tradition is to look down
and don't look at them just pretend
they're not there okay don't go like
okay
there was a linguist that came i think
after you guys three
year retreat they wanted to study how
you communicate
like this you know
that's a whole new language you know
they're like
so that's the same as talking really
okay so
don't do it okay
it's a custom just to look down and keep
walking okay
uh
and don't talk
obviously you shouldn't turn on your
cell phone the whole time okay just turn
it off and put it away
and you can take it out when you get
back okay when you start again okay so
in the first few
retreats
of this lamrim series we took away
people's cell phone and laptop
then one day some lady said her laptop's
missing
we spent
two days looking for her laptop we
couldn't find it
and then i think she thought we stole it
and then she went home and she found it
in her bathroom
uh
then we stopped taking people's laptops
if you want a good retreat
turn it off put it away okay
if you don't want a good retreat use it
and you know you're all over 16 years
old i think katie yeah
so
you know you're all adults i'm just
telling you if if you think you have
some important computer thing to do
during the three days you will have a
lousy retreat the retreat won't help you
much okay
put it away you know put away the
computer
put away the phone
just
do it okay and i can't
i may spy on you i do that
i'm good at it
uh
in the retreat but
i can't be in your house you know
so it's up to you
it's up to you what do you want from
this retreat if you don't want a very
deep retreat
then do some computer work or or do some
texting okay
look at wechat wechat is the retreat
destroyer machine
okay wechat is retreat destroyer machine
okay you
you know so so please i mean i really
really encourage you just to give it up
okay
try it
you will have a good time you will enjoy
it
why did we build a retreat center
in this
god-awful place
of rocks and sun
it's because it's one of the last places
in the united states where cell phone
coverage doesn't cover
really okay and it's it's like two hours
to the grocery store right
so uh
don't waste our time you know we we put
the retreat center here
so you wouldn't use your cell phone
now that we cell phone towers are
chasing us
and
some places i know where they are you
can get cell phone reception
in my outhouse you can get
a cell phone reception
okay but uh just forget it okay it's up
to you
what kind of retreat you want okay and
i'm talking also to the older students
the older students are as bad as the new
students
they're like i'm special i don't
i'm older student
i'm special i can use computer
just forget it
okay it's a disease of older dharma
students i'm so advanced i can use
laptop during retreat
forget it okay it's wrong okay all right
all right
so mantras at 4 15 walking around if you
want but you just had a walk so it
should be okay
dinner at 5 15. don't eat too much
because you get very tired in the
evening 6 15
uh
do the thousand angels from the middle
of this book if you don't have this book
buy one if you don't have this book buy
one if you don't have this book buy one
if you don't have any money we'll give
it to you okay
but don't go into retreat without this
you want to hear a tibetan joke
so there was a war a war in tibet means
three people attacked two people or
something like that okay
they didn't have very good wars
then uh
so this guy
heard there was a war so he he got his
gun his rifle
and he started to walk to east about you
know to fight with somebody
and then
on the way
he had the poo-poo
and he asked the farmer can i use your
outhouse
and he went in the outhouse and he uh
put his gun down and he made a poopoo
and then he left but he forgot his gun
and then just after that he met the two
enemy guys
and he reached for his gun
and it was gone
and then he's so scared he made a poo
poo
so they say
what he left his gun where he shed it
and he where he should have had
his gun
or something like that
okay and it's a tibetan joke for uh
what's up
[Music]
uh
don't forget your gun
okay
when you go to
dharma war you gotta have your gun
okay this is your gun
okay there's three pairs this is the
gun
[Music]
capac
it sounds better in tibetan
okay
uh
all right
okay 8 15 you do
uh what are we up to twenty one to
[Music]
do the next five
do the next five choose something from
the next fight
is it the fifth set
oh i'm talking about yeah you're right
okay after dinner fourth set
of five meditations
uh
seven fifty just do multiply times five
okay
do the next five don't try to do all
five you don't have time pick one
okay pick the one that's most sexy to
you okay
8 15
pick another five
okay
and then nine o'clock
when i did my three year retreat i i
stayed in europe for three years
i think the yurt is still there i think
we should take it down to be honest
and maybe i can help or something uh
i think we should just take down all the
things that are not being used because
they don't they make the place look
trashy or something
uh
so anything we're not using
you know that's falling apart we should
just
we should make the place clean you know
it's like having junk in your house um
anyway
uh
it's very very nice to do mantras under
the stars
so you can take a chair outside
and just look
at the sky
and watch the stars and uh
i know especially in china you
oftentimes you can can cannot see the
stars in in phoenix where i grew up you
cannot see the stars because of the city
light
so uh
i think it's very good for your uh
spiritual life if you
enjoy the stars the color chakra tantra
says that okay
so uh
you know spend some time enjoy the start
here okay go outside
dress warm
the desert gets very cold at night as
you know
it changes how many degrees 30 degrees
40 degrees
so you have to
a good meditator in the desert has lots
of layers
you know
they have t-shirt then they have a shirt
then they have an over shirt
then they have a sweater then they have
a shawl
and when it in the morning they have
everything then at 10 o'clock they take
off the show
and at 11 o'clock they take off the
sweater
and 12 o'clock they take off the shirt
you know and then they put it back on at
five o'clock six o'clock
so so that's the
that's how people meditate don't get
cold on the floor meditating okay make
sure you don't get cold that's not good
for you okay
uh
i forgot to mention you know as you know
but i'm gonna say it again there are
snakes here
in the desert and they are poisonous
okay they're called rattlesnake
they have these two teeth
they have a injection
uh poison okay serious poison
so uh
so you have to be careful not to step on
them they are peaceful they don't want
to
you are too big to eat
they use the poison to kill small
animals
and to and then they eat them the
joggles aren't
and uh but they when they see a human
they don't want to hurt you because
there's a waste their energy
they cannot eat you so they will not
hurt you
and and they will give you warning it's
called it sounds like can anybody do it
they have a little thing on their tail
they go
and if you hear it stop
don't walk
and find out where are they and then
just turn around and go the other way
okay don't say oh what's that
i think 90 percent of people who get
bitten are trying to play with them or
they're trying to push them or
okay so it's very rare they will bite
you we had in my three year retreat
we had many many snakes one night i had
five
around my in inside my fence
and they won't hurt you but don't step
on them okay and they they're hard to
see
so look where you put your feet okay
like don't step over
a rock or a log you cannot see what's on
the other side okay all right so be
careful with them
if you get bit or if you have an
emergency make a lot of noise and
someone will come and help you okay
we had one person in our retreat got bit
uh on her finger right here
you know and she had to go to the
hospital so
trying not to
i think so far we've been pretty lucky
yeah
but i don't want you to be the first one
okay
uh
and that's part of having a retreat
center in a wild place we can have the
retreat center in the city
and you can't have a good retreat
because it's too noisy
there's too many cars and too much
energy
when you go to the country you have
animals
and
you have to share your space because
they were here first
okay so we have to respect their rights
also okay
okay wednesday
get up a little bit earlier okay
so you have to watch your schedule i
moved it earlier every day
and uh don't eat before your first
meditation just have some tea
don't have if you can
stop black stop black tea stop coffee
during the three days okay
it's not good for your meditation
okay
uh then do the georgia the first part
from here
then go back to the first five
meditations
maybe choose a different one okay
then do your yoga
then light breakfast then goof off very
well
then do the second part of this with the
next five meditations okay juice
same schedule okay
uh for wednesday thursday
uh
same schedule in the morning
up until
10 45 and then we'll start right melissa
we'll start bringing you back to the
temple
okay
and then you can have uh
at 11 30 we'll do a short ceremony
to open the
boundaries okay
and before you come down
on the bus
you have to take the boundary markers
off of your cabin okay
why
they block traffic
okay
spirits cannot move good spirits bad
spirit nobody can move it's like stop
science everywhere
so if
they really work
there for real they really stop spirits
and they're irritated they don't like
them
because they can't go everywhere okay so
it's important to take them off of your
cabin
take them off the opposite way that you
put them up
okay first one in front of your door the
side of your front door take that one
off first
then go to the right
so if if this is my door
i will take that one off first
then i'll take this one off
the opposite of how i put them on
then i'll take this one off and then
i'll take that one off okay
what do you do with them they are like
scripture they have holy words on them
one of your refuge vows
is to treat anything with holy words on
it as buddha's speech okay
so
don't throw them in the garbage okay i
like to keep them
in my house you know then i look at them
sometimes oh that was
1985.
grand canyon retreat that was a good one
you know
i like to keep them
you know there's kind of good luck for
people who are sick or something
when you get home you can give them to
a sick person put it on their bed or
something
and it's good for them okay
it has a good energy
all right
then uh
after that we'll take a group photo so
don't forget try to look beautiful at 11
45 on thursday then you can go back to
normal at 12.
okay so try to dress nice okay
for the photograph okay
and then we'll have some more classes
okay
um
we cut this retreat by one day because
we had a special event
uh after it
uh which was cancelled but it was too
late to change it so it was the second
term
at the college but we made the terms
longer and we made less terms okay
so sorry about that all right
let's go
what time do we stop tim 8 45
8 30
8 30.
well i was gonna give you questions but
i talked too much which is usual
so let's do some scripture okay
uh
[Music]
uh nick i'm on
m-i-d-a-n-g-m-i
me down meeman
yeah that's it
let's go there okay this is one of the
benefits of taking refuge okay ready
hang in there you got 45 minutes
let's use the time
me
this is part
of
meditation
number
[Music]
okay which means uh
if you're if you're
taking refuge regularly if you're using
the four steps
regularly then spirits can't harm you
much
and people cannot harm you much okay
why
just always go back to the second
husband
okay because you understand where
they're coming from
so they get less
you know shanti deva complained
i don't like this four steps
his teacher said why
he said
i don't have any enemies to be patient
with
it just gets less and less every week
you know i don't like this system
how am i supposed to
become more patient if i don't have any
enemies
you know okay
it will get less and less okay
so there's a demon
who
uses a special power called lung shock
lung means uh
what
wind
shakba means
lasso like a cowboy in a rodeo
okay
to catch things with a rope
okay and uh if he puts this on you
you you start to have sickness and
things like that okay
so there was a
there was some bad guy chasing a
buddhist uh
kenyan
lifetime layman's vow person
and he was chasing him with this special
noose
trying to cause him trouble
luck manipa means uh
he couldn't pull it off it's an idiom in
tibetan okay he
couldn't get get it
it the news didn't work on the
on the guy okay the spirit couldn't hurt
him
you want to hear the whole story
uh i found it
okay
here's the story
of the guy who tried to catch the
buddhist with his noose okay
um
there was a
non-buddhist guy mean guy
dupe
and he reached some kind of special bad
powers
lungi sharpa star with sharp chin and
that
bad spirit gave him this special
magic rope
okay
they come at up
if he catches you with that rope you
have to do what he says you can't refuse
okay
nobody okay
lanchy
la tape
then
he saw a mother with a small child in
her arms
and he thought i will take control of
the child
so he put the
rope over the childhood
but
it didn't work
okay the rope didn't work sharp but they
decked said chiwei chiba de la that came
up to that time
every person he put the rope on died
he killed them
but he put the rope on the kid and
nothing happened okay
then uh
ona
then the
this bad guy started to think maybe my
magic rope lost its power okay
ki chic pot big bay
so he he saw a dog
and he put the rope around the dog's
neck
uh dema talk shiwee and immediately dog
died
so he said okay so my rope is okay
it's not a
what do you call it malfunction rope
uh
then he asked uh
i forget it doesn't say who he asked
yeah anyway maybe he asked the buddha or
something you know what's so special
about this kid
young man this kid has no other powers
that capsule somehow she in
when he was very
young
he had an idea of taking refuge okay
this kid took refuge once
correctly
okay
so
it's not gonna work
your rope won't work on him okay so it
means if you take refuge
they can't hurt you
okay
and the story ends the bad guy became a
good buddhist
okay
uh
gagana
then in
india
they didn't bury people
they just threw them in a field
burial
ground and they didn't bury them under
the ground they just throw the dead body
in this field okay
and then that became a very
frightening place because animals would
come to eat the bodies you know like
dangerous animals who come to eat their
bodies at night
so it used to be a punishment
like if somebody stole something and the
king want to punish them they make them
stay in that field the whole night okay
then generally anybody they threw in
that field would be carried away by evil
spirits
okay and killed and eaten
nobody survived
then he found a little piece of uh
somebody's robe
this
buddhist robe
in the graveyard he found this little
piece he put it on his head
then he said i take refuge in buddha i
take refuge in dharma a whole night
and spirits couldn't touch him
okay
then you guys don't believe in spirits
and i'm sorry but they exist and they
cause a lot of trouble okay
and it's not some kind of superstition
there's a joke in hell
that the greatest thing that
demons have done in this world in the
last couple hundred years is make people
think they don't exist
that's their best accomplishment
in this world okay it's kind of funny
all right they they're very what do you
call happy about that
they don't believe in us up there
so we can do whatever we want
okay
then there was a
nomad
sheep heard her
in tibet
and
he was sleeping outside and one night a
bear
caught him
we have bears here also
you don't want to meet them okay
and she like had to che almost killed
him
okay
if you see a bear just turn around and
walk the other way okay
just turn around
don't go
running because they like it
okay just back up and walk away okay
hi
bye
i think there's not any right now around
okay
don't worry
but and he got a terrible scar on his
face
from the bear attack
okay
lama shiki
they give chipana
and one mama asked him why you have this
scar on your face you know
called logia
and he told the lama the story oh i was
sleeping and a bear caught me in
then lame came down
then the llama said
next time
tried
doing the refuge
okay
probably he's saying it's so bad that
the bear ran away i don't know
uh
he taught him to do the prayer chi shi
yang kyar tehran two
cup
then he ran into another bear later
kim do che pe he did the sangge chodo
and sokito nama okay
and the jay day
means
then the bear was smelling to find him
sometimes the wild animals here find you
by smell they cannot find you they don't
have good eyes
so they're like
but he couldn't uh find him
and he just left okay
one time i met a deer in the forest i
was doing retreat and
we just both stopped i stopped he
stopped you know and he's looking at me
and i'm looking at him you know
then i thought
let's see how he likes mandala offering
because in the buddhist scripture it
says they like songs
you know and i sang him the mandala and
he was like
and he stayed to the whole mandala it
was very beautiful
quiet moment in the forest and he's just
like
you know they like it animals like
singing
and everybody likes mandala
okay
uh
what time after that 8 30
8 15.
oh man
okay i'm gonna keep going okay i know
you're tired so am i let's just keep
going uh kim daok
sometimes
so there was
a buddhist name anata pandana
who is that
yeah
he bought
he he bought the park for the
buddha
where the buddha taught
the diamond cutter okay
anata means people who have nobody to
help them pindata means gives them food
his name is mr gives food to people who
have nobody to help them that's his name
another panda okay then uh
he learned how to say sange children's
okay
okay in sanskrit i don't know what it is
but he learned how to say
ten more due to to songwrite
and he was stuck in a
dangerous
burial ground at night
and because he recited the
sangeet children
he could see a path through the
graveyard
and he got away me me manuba
the spirits couldn't hurt him
okay
then one day he uh
prostrated
to
a stupa not buddha stupa okay
and he lost that power
okay and nyambe love you okay
uh
young get on
shanky
ray
this is a cute story
uh
so there was uh
uh what do you call a monk
and someone gave him a
cloth to make new ropes okay
and then a
a robber
saw him
carrying the cloth home
then the robber came at night to steal
the cloth
geylong top cheney then the
monk was kind of strong
and he caught him
means he tied his hands
and koen joseon
lansing
then he took a big stick and he said
uh
i take refuge in the buddha i take
refuge in the dharma i take refuge in
the sangha
and he beat him each time one time
so he got hit on the head three hard
times buddha dharma
okay
let's see
today
and then the
thief ran away
you know he's got three bumps on his
head
and uh
me my ambiguous
then he went and hid under a bridge
and that bridge at night was used by
many bad spirits it was a highway
for bad spirits at night so actually
very dangerous place to
stop but he didn't know that so he
went to the bridge he hid under the
bridge
and these very dangerous spirits are
coming and going on the bridge
then he was
talking to himself you know he said that
monk he hit me three times he said
buddha dhamma sangha
you know they assume they may have a
dublin
i'm glad there's only three jewels
if there was more than three jewels he
would have killed me
and he just said it quietly to himself
he's like i don't know he's yelling he's
then because he's repeating those three
words the spirits couldn't touch him
otherwise they would kill him
but he kept saying to himself stupid mom
with a buddha
dharma
what do you say
then the
spirits couldn't hurt him because he's
saying this good word
okay
kind of funny
and
the words also caused the traffic jam on
the bridge
because the spirits couldn't go past it
so they got really upset with him
because they can't go past the place
where someone's reciting buddha
okay
all right this uh
so then he gets serious and he says
people like us
if you get into a really dangerous
situation okay somebody's pointing a gun
at you or something okay i don't know
it happened to me another time you know
somebody had a gun they were gonna shoot
me
and uh
you know that moment
somebody's got the gun at you you know
then at that moment he says
don't get freaked out don't worry you've
got refuge okay load them
lowden means you have a
dharma
insurance policy
okay deng means insurance like
guarantee or insurance okay
just think of the buddha dharma sangha
okay
and captain
cheney council good
and stick to that
those three buddha dharma sangha and you
don't have to worry okay
so it's good to have it ready
[Music]
also it can stop you from going to a
lower rebirth
there was a
young man living in the lands of the
devas okay worldly gods
and they have a
a thing that just before they die they
can see where they're going they're
called kapsumba sometimes
and one of the most famous prayers of
songkapa is called kapsumba
kapsumba means
three
three times
they can see where they are now they can
see where they came from and they can
see where they're going okay
it's a it's a synonym for deva
uh three timers
okay
uh
so
their suffering is very
great because they can see where they're
going to go after they die okay
and he saw he's going to be born as a
pig
bush
so he went to he took refuge in the
chakra which is like indra okay
and uh who who themselves is in samsara
okay they're just in a better samsara
for a while
they kept my new part but he
indra knew he couldn't help protect him
so indra went to the buddha
and said can you help this guy he's
praying to me i don't have
the power to help him okay
sange you came to dumba
then the buddha came and thought about
taking refuge to the young
deva
and high view candor cheshire and then
the deva
young deva young god
he died taking refuge
okay
jason judging the kind of kid duke
tapana
uh
then chakra decided to check where was
he reborn
okay this powerful god
want to check where was he reborn
son nam kilrang
and he couldn't find him
in all the realms of the universe okay
he checked the whole
universe and he couldn't find him
because it's the nature of people at
those high levels
that they can only see the people below
them
they can't see the people above there
you see i mean
they open up
lord buddha
where is this guy i can't find him i
don't see where he was reborn
then buddha said
he's busy he's in to shira
he went to shira
okay and that's above your place so you
can't see him okay
so he was supposed to be born as a pig
but he died with buddha's name
on his lips so he was born in toshida
okay
modern people don't believe in toshita
they don't believe they can be a pig
they don't believe in all okay i'm
not only was he not born as a pig
he was born in this divine realm
then pablo rinpoche said i taught you
guys
every single class
you start with
sange turned on
he says i'm trying to help you
okay i want it burned into your brain
okay because
if you just think of it when you're
dying you won't go down
okay he said i just
that's why i told you you have to do
this pair every single class okay
i'm talking
okay you ready
in the monastery
[Music]
and they don't think about it once
they reach we decide 21 in a row
before the debates and it's amazing
nobody's listening to it at all
it's amazing i mean some people probably
okay
but don't get in this bad habit before
uh
class
somebody starts a sangeet children sorry
and you're just like
okay think about the meaning okay
what's the meaning of the mandala before
class
what's the meaning
yeah offering a perfect world it means
uh
when the people put their hands like
this
you're supposed to imagine a world where
everybody is using the fourth depth
everybody whole world
okay
every businessman is trying to
make other businessmen successful
every country
is trying to make other countries
successful okay
everybody who wants
a cute girlfriend is trying not to hurt
other people's relationship
okay and then the whole world
is like heaven
okay because the whole world's using the
fort
so the whole world is taking refuge so
when you do the mandala
just think about it okay
this is uh
dci reached i don't know
africa
and everybody's using the force death
okay like think like that okay don't
waste your time
okay
offer a perfect world
that's meaning of mandala okay mandala
means
a world
where everybody's taking refuge
okay i got the whole story from the khan
gear it's not that interesting
so i'm not gonna spend the time okay
it's pretty long
and if you want to i'll give it to you
you can try to translate it
uh it's pretty long
okay
it's called the story of the
the story of the
[Music]
wild pig okay it's a sutra
it's long
and the story is in there okay
uh
last thing okay
i still got
eight minutes right
[Music]
okay this is some tantric deep tantric
thing
okay
and you're supposed to go like this
you know
making fun of those guys
okay he says all those guys tantric
college you know
having this deep meditation they're
hoping the sponsor is looking at them
not everybody okay it's just possible
i'm not saying
some of them really are having
tantric experience i believe done
but it's possible some are not serious
okay possible i'm not saying all the
monks are like that they're not
those monasteries are the most blessed
place on the earth okay and what's
happening there is unbelievable
and everybody should try it
there's no place like that in the world
okay but there are some fake guys okay i
think so
anyway he said that
uh make something subject make tsum tsum
means like this
with your eyes you know and then uh
means uh fake it z-o-b just look for
z-o-b
space
space z-o-b you got it
uh
space z-o-b
there you go
uh
sub-tipping
you are demonstrating by your tantric
practice
that you don't understand
how it is
that you become a buddhist
okay by this deep deep tantric practice
you are
showing
say cooktop10
10. my llama used to tell it to me all
the time
uh
cook means idiot
i taught you that shinto koopa
yeah cook talk ten means uh
if you're a fool
and you walk into a room of
wise people
you're okay if you keep your mouth shut
they won't realize you're a fool you see
so if you like walk into a room with a
bunch of really great llamas
keep your mouth shut you know and maybe
they think you're the same
okay
but if you open your mouth and you start
to talk that's called uh
advertising your koopa
[Music]
okay advertising you are kookba
okay so pabongkorn said
people who do this deep tantric practice
they are ringing bells and banging
things you know
you know
uh he said
you know better you didn't say anything
we we might have thought you were wise
got it
okay
he said
you want to show your intelligence
you want to show your real tantrica
you know it's not with this
all these american people if somebody
rings a bell or wears a special hat they
all run there and they give money and
they take initiations you know
it's funny
they don't even know the teacher the
teacher doesn't know them they don't get
their vows
[Music]
they just pay some money
and they think because the llamas
banging on things and
say some strange words they think oh
this must be special okay
pablo grim pj says
what's special
is the second husband
okay
that's a high tantrica
okay come home
husband says you're idiot and you go you
yeah yeah okay
all right
that's okay that's a tantrica
okay got it
they don't have this one they're not
ringing a bell they don't have special
you know
it's amazing how many people get
excited by
bell and they're ringing boom boom boom
and
wow oh they must be very big llama you
know
and i'm not saying it pablanca is saying
it you know
pabonga says
the wife who comes home
and
stops what she wa phantom
stops to call her husband stupid
that's a tantrum
that's a tantrica
not these big guys with the crowns and
the bells and
okay really really that wife who comes
home
and understands the emptiness
of her husband is more advanced
okay got it she's more advanced
she's really practicing the root of
tantra
okay
got it
that's very cool
and it's true okay
it's true
okay we'll stop there that's a cool
place to stop okay if you stop yourself
from hurting someone who hurt you
because you realize
you made them
[Music]
you're a high secret buddhist
okay
you are more advanced than all those
tantrusts okay
got it
all right